<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<header>
        <title>
	Apache Lucene - Building and Installing the Basic Demo
		</title>
	</header>
<properties>
<author email="acoliver@apache.org">Andrew C. Oliver</author>
</properties>
<body>

<section id="About this Document"><title>About this Document</title>
<p>
This document is intended as a "getting started" guide to using and running the Lucene demos.
It walks you through some basic installation and configuration.
</p>
</section>


<section id="About the Demos"><title>About the Demos</title>
<p>
The Lucene command-line demo code consists of two applications that demonstrate various
functionalities of Lucene and how one should go about adding Lucene to their applications.
</p>
</section>

<section id="Setting your CLASSPATH"><title>Setting your CLASSPATH</title>
<p>
First, you should <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lucene/java/">download</a> the
latest Lucene distribution and then extract it to a working directory.  Alternatively, you can <a
href="http://wiki.apache.org/lucene-java/SourceRepository">check out the sources from
Subversion</a>, and then run <code>ant war-demo</code> to generate the JARs and WARs.
</p>
<p>
You should see the Lucene JAR file in the directory you created when you extracted the archive.  It
should be named something like <code>lucene-core-{version}.jar</code>.  You should also see a file
called <code>lucene-demos-{version}.jar</code>.  If you checked out the sources from Subversion then
the JARs are located under the <code>build</code> subdirectory (after running <code>ant</code>
successfully).  Put both of these files in your Java CLASSPATH.
</p>
</section>

<section id="Indexing Files"><title>Indexing Files</title>
<p>
Once you've gotten this far you're probably itching to go.  Let's <b>build an index!</b> Assuming
you've set your CLASSPATH correctly, just type:

<pre>
    java org.apache.lucene.demo.IndexFiles {full-path-to-lucene}/src
</pre>

This will produce a subdirectory called <code>index</code> which will contain an index of all of the
Lucene source code.
</p>
<p>
To <b>search the index</b> type:

<pre>
    java org.apache.lucene.demo.SearchFiles
</pre>

You'll be prompted for a query.  Type in a swear word and press the enter key.  You'll see that the
Lucene developers are very well mannered and get no results. Now try entering the word "string".
That should return a whole bunch of documents.  The results will page at every tenth result and ask
you whether you want more results.
</p>
</section>

<section id="About the code..."><title>About the code...</title>
<p>
<a href="demo2.html">read on&gt;&gt;&gt;</a>
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

