<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
<properties>
<author email="acoliver@apache.org">Andrew C. Oliver</author>
<title>Jakarta Lucene - Building and Installing the Basic Demo</title>
</properties>
<body>

<section name="About this Document">
<p>
This document is intended as a "getting started" guide to installing and running the
Jakarta Lucene web application demo.  This guide assumes that you have read the
information in the previous two examples or already know it anyhow.  We'll use 
Tomcat 4.0.1 as our reference web container.  These demos should work with nearly
any container, but it is up to you to adapt them appropriately.
</p>
</section>


<section name="About the Demos">
<p>
The Lucene Web Application demo is a template web application intended for deployment
on Tomcat or a similar web container.  It's NOT designed as a "best practices"
implementation by ANY means.  It's more of a "hello world" type Lucene Web App.  
The purpose of this application is to demonstrate Lucene.  With that being said, 
it should be relatively simple to create a small searchable website in Tomcat or 
a similar application server.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Indexing Files">
<p> 
Once you've gotten this far you're probably itching to go.  
Let's start by creating the  index you'll need for the web examples.  
Since you've already set your classpath in the previous examples, 
all you need to do is type 
<b> "java org.apache.lucene.demo.IndexHTML -create -index {index-dir} .."</b>.
You'll need to do this from a (any) subdirectory of your {tomcat}/webapps directory (make sure you didn't leave off the ".." or you'll get a null pointer
exception). 
{index-dir}
should be a directory that Tomcat has permission to read and write, but is
outside of a web accessible context.  By default the webapp is configured
to look in <b>/opt/lucene/index</b> for this index.  
</p>
</section>

<section name="Deploying the Demos">
<p>Located in your distribution directory you should see
a war file called luceneweb.war.  Copy this to your 
{tomcat-home}/webapps directory.  You may need to restart 
Tomcat.  </p>
</section>

<section name="Configuration">
<p> 
From your Tomcat directory look in the webapps/luceneweb subdirectory.  If it's not 
present, try browsing to "http://localhost:8080/luceneweb" then look again.  
Edit a file called configuration.jsp.  Ensure that the indexLocation is equal to the 
location you used for your index.  You may also customize the appTitle and appFooter 
strings as you see fit.  Once you have finished altering the configuration you should 
restart Tomcat.  You may also wish to update the war file by typing 
<b>jar -uf luceneweb.war configuration.jsp</b> from the luceneweb subdirectory.  
(The -u option is not available in all versions of jar.  In this case recreate the war file).
</p>
</section>

<section name="Running the Demos">
<p>Now you're ready to roll.  In your browser set the url to "http://localhost:8080/luceneweb"
enter "test" and the number of items per page and press search.</p>
<p>You should now be looking either at a number of results (provided you didn't erase the 
Tomcat examples) or nothing.  Try other search terms.  Depending on the number of items 
per page you set and results returned, there may be a link at the bottom that says "more results>>",
clicking it goes to subsequent pages.  If you get an error regarding opening the index, then you
probably set the path in "configuration" incorrectly or Tomcat doesn't have permissions to the 
index (or you skipped the step of creating it).</p>
</section>

<section name="About the code...">
<p>
If you want to know more about how this web app works or how to customize it then 
<a href="demo4.html">read on&gt;&gt;&gt;</a>.
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

