<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
<properties>
<author email="acoliver@apache.org">Andrew C. Oliver</author>
<title>Apache Lucene - Building and Installing the Basic Demo</title>
</properties>
<body>

<section name="About this Document">
<p>
This document is intended as a "getting started" guide to using and running the
Apache Lucene demos.  It walks you through some basic installation and configuration.
</p>
</section>


<section name="About the Demos">
<p>
The Lucene Demo code is a set of command line example applications that demonstrate various 
functionality of Lucene and how one should go about adding it to their 
applications.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Setting your classpath">
<p>
First, extract the latest Lucene distribution.  
</p>
<p>
You should see the Apache Lucene jar file in the directory you created 
when you extracted the archive.  It should be named something like
<b>lucene-{version}.jar</b>.  
</p>
<p>
You should also see a file called called <b>lucene-demos-{version}.jar</b>.  
Put both of these files in your Java CLASSPATH.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Indexing Files">
<p>
Once you've gotten this far you're probably itching to go.  Let's <b> build an index!</b>
Assuming you've set your classpath correctly, just type 
"java org.apache.lucene.demo.IndexFiles {full-path-to-lucene}/src". This will produce 
a subdirectory called "index" which will contain an index of all of the Lucene 
sourcecode. 
</p>
<p>
<b> To search the index </b> type "java org.apache.lucene.demo.SearchFiles".  You'll be prompted
for a query.  Type in a swear word and press the enter key.  You'll see that the Lucene 
developers are very well mannered and get no results. Now try entering the word "vector".
That should return a whole bunch of documents.  The results will page at every tenth
result and ask you whether you want more results.
</p>
</section>

<section name="About the code...">
<p>
<a href="demo2.html">read on&gt;&gt;&gt;</a>
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

