<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
<properties>
<author email="acoliver@apache.org">Andrew C. Oliver</author>
<title>Jakarta Lucene - Getting Started Guide</title>
</properties>
<body>

<section name="About this Document">
<p>
This document is intended as a "getting started" guide.  It has three basic 
audiences: novices looking to install Jakarta Lucene on their application or 
web server, developers looking to modify or base the applications they develop
on Lucene, and developers looking to become involved in and contribute to the
development of Lucene.  This document is written in tutorial and walkthrough 
format.  It intends to help you in "getting started", but does not go into great
depth into some of the conceptual or inner details of Jakarta Lucene.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Format of this Guide">
<p>
Each section listed below builds on one another.  That being said more advanced users may
wish to skip sections.  
</p>
</section>

<section name="The Simple Demo">
<p>
In <a href="demo.html">this</a> section we walk through the basic Lucene demo and executing it.  
This section is intended for anyone who wants a basic background on using the provided Lucene demos.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Simple Demo Source Walkthrough">
<p>
In <a href="demo2.html">this</a> section we walk through the sources and implementation
for the basic Lucene demo.  This section is intended for developers.  
</p>
</section>

<section name="Template Web Application">
<p>
In <a href="demo3.html">this</a> section we walk through installing 
and configuring the template web application.  While this walkthough assumes 
Tomcat 4.0.x as your container of choice, there is no reason you can't (provided you have
the requisite knowledge) adapt the instructions to your container.  This section is intended
for those responsible for the development or deployment of Lucene-based web applications.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Template Web Application sources">
<p>
In <a href="demo4.html">this</a> section we walk through the sources used to construct the 
template web application.  Please note the template application is designed to highlight 
features of Lucene and is <b>not</b> an example of best practices.  (One would hopefully 
use MVC architecture such as provided by Jakarta Struts and taglibs, or better yet XML 
with stylesheets, but showing you how to do that would be WAY beyond the scope of this 
demonstration.  Additionally once could cache results, and perform other performance 
optimizations, but those are beyond the scope of this demo).
</p>
<p>  
This section is intended for developers and those wishing to customize the template web 
application to their needs.  The sections useful to developers only are clearly delineated.
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>

